Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching The Plain Bagel. Over the past
decade, we've seen the buildout of a
massive lending machine outside of the
traditional banking system. You may have
heard of terms like shadow banking or
NBFIs, non-bank financial
intermediaries, or specifically in this
case, private credit. But they all
generally refer to the same idea of
non-bank institutions carrying out
functions that would traditionally be
provided by banks. With private credit,
whereby these non-bank institutions lend
money directly to private businesses,
seen particularly strong growth. With
the area up until recently being, quote,
"the hot new thing on Wall Street."
However, with a fraction of the
oversight and regulation, over the last
few months, we've started to see some
cracks form. Uh, from private borrower
defaults and write-offs to a rush for
the exits by private credit investors,
so much so that funds have begun
restricting withdrawals. There's this
growing concern that this fast-growing
segment of the financial system
may have taken on too much risk.
Something that's led the stock prices
for the companies running these private
credit funds, including Blackstone, KKR,
and Blue Owl, to drop anywhere from 20
to over 50%
since September. With us once again
seeing warnings that things are starting
to look a little pre-2008
financial crisis-y. Uh, which with
everything else going on at this time
doesn't make too many people all that
optimistic. So, what's happening here?
Is this just an example of markets
getting spooked? Or is there a more
systemic issue at play here?
Well, that's a great question. And one
that's unfortunately tricky to answer,
given the whole private part of private
credit. We don't actually have that much
insight into the area, given its opaque
nature. But today, we'll cover what we
have seen happen, why investors are
scrambling to get their money out, uh,
what we do know about the financial
health of private credit companies, and
some important considerations to help
put things into perspective. Not to
convince you one way or another about
the health of the market or where things
are going to go from here, but just to
give some important context when you
hear claims of us going through another
repeat of the financial crisis. But,
let's start at the beginning. What
exactly is private credit? Well, while
the name could technically refer to any
debt that's just not publicly traded,
and there are varying definitions in
terms of what technically counts as
private credit, the term essentially
refers to the lending equivalent of
private equity. Private equity is when
investment firms raise a bunch of
investor capital, buy private companies,
and then pass the returns onto
investors, charging exorbitant fees in
the process. And private credit is when
investment firms raise a bunch of
investor capital, lend to private
companies, and then pass the returns
onto investors, charging exorbitant fees
in the process. And as mentioned, it's
been a very fast-growing industry.
McKinsey estimates that private credit
has grown tenfold from 2009 to 2023.
With some estimates pinning the size of
the US market, which makes up the lion's
share of the global market, at around $2
trillion,
which compares to today's US corporate
bond market of roughly $11 trillion.
Now, part of the reason we've seen the
industry growing this segment so quickly
is
yes, those exorbitant fees mentioned
earlier, but also because the area is
helping to fill an important gap that's
been left by traditional banks following
the 2008 financial crisis. You see,
after the Great Recession, banks were
slapped with new, stringent regulations
that restricted the risk they could take
on with their assets to ensure that they
could absorb losses with their capital
if need be. Something that incentivized
banks to move away from riskier lending
activities like business lending and
towards safer things like Treasury bonds
and higher-quality mortgage back
securities, which are treated favorably
under the new standards. And while these
regulations did decrease the systemic
risk of the banking system, it also
resulted in shifting this riskier
lending activity to a more opaque and
less regulated part of the market,
private credit, who were happy to fill
the gap left behind. Uh for them, it
meant higher fees for any deal flow they
experienced, even at times regardless of
how the underlying loans performed. And
for the investors whose money was used
to fund these loans, it was a compelling
pitch. Private credit funds would use
those exorbitant fees to hire the
best-in-class analysts, engage, analyze,
and negotiate with businesses directly
to find the best lending opportunities,
and earn investors a return higher than
what was otherwise available with
traditional bonds in the market.
Blackstone's flagship private credit
fund, for example, has provided a return
of 9.8% annually since its inception,
which for something viewed as a
fixed-income investment, even though
there was naturally much more risk than
traditional investment-grade bonds, was
very compelling when publicly traded
bonds were offering low single-digit
yields. But over the last few months,
the space has experienced a bit of a
reckoning. Now, there have been
questions and concerns around private
equity and private credit for quite some
time, given the opaque nature of their
operations, but this past September
concerns were reignited when we saw two
companies, car dealership and subprime
lender Tricolor and car parts supplier
First Brands, declare bankruptcy on
combined debts of over $10 billion,
uh, triggering a number of private
credit lenders and investment funds to
realize sizable losses. Now, of course,
any one bankruptcy, or even two in this
case, isn't itself all that concerning,
especially in the private credit space,
where fund managers take on more risk,
and workouts and bankruptcies are part
of what the funds are prepared to work
through. But what raised a few eyebrows
with this situation was how quickly
private creditors went from expecting
full repayment of these loans to writing
off the vast majority of their value. In
fact, 6 months prior to First Brands
bankruptcy, the company was given a
quote clean bill of health in an audit
provided by BDO, with value of the debt
plummeting after the bankruptcy from
par, or around 100 cents on the dollar,
to below 20 cents. And Tricolor's own
asset-backed bonds were previously rated
by Kroll Bond Rating Agency as AAA, the
highest credit rating out there, before
they were cut straight to deep junk on
the bankruptcy news. Now, executives for
both of these companies have actually
since been charged with fraud in
connection to their collapse, the
companies allegedly double pledging
their assets as collateral for their
loans. But naturally, the whole thing
raises concerns over the due diligence
and lending standards of the
institutions who lent money to these
businesses and all smells a little too
similar to what we saw with the 2008
financial crisis where lax lending
standards and questionable bond ratings
played an important role in the subprime
mortgage crisis. And while with First
Brands specifically, loans were actually
predominantly financed by public market
lending with only 2% of First Brands
debt coming from private credit, it
nonetheless raised concerns with the
biggest question at the time being, how
prevalent are these risky loans in the
system? JP Morgan CEO Jamie Dimon, for
example, whose bank took a $170 million
hit in connection to Tricolor, famously
commented at the time that, "When you
see one cockroach, there's probably
more." And it turns out that he was
right because not long after January, we
saw Apollo Global Management report a
loss on a portion of $170 million loan
for an Amazon aggregator Perch that was
written off to zero despite the loan
being backed by assets and layered to
include additional protections. And in
March, BlackRock reported that it had
completely written off a loan to
Infinite Commerce Holdings. This despite
the loan being assessed at 100 cents on
the dollar just 3 months prior. And it's
painted a pretty concerning trend. Fitch
reported earlier this month that
defaults among corporate private credit
borrowers had reached a new high of 9.2%
up from 8.1% in 2024 and even rising
above the level seen during the
pandemic. Now, Morgan Stanley's
estimates put default rates at a lower
4.5% as of December, but sees this rate
reaching 8%, which likewise would put it
above 2020 highs. So, yeah, you can see
why there are concerns about the space
and why we've seen a wave of investors
whose money is stuck in these loans
trying to get their money out. Uh
specifically, we've seen redemption
requests from investors in
retail-focused private credit funds
reach new all-time highs. And the
pressure from the withdrawals has led
many of these funds to gate redemptions.
I've summarized a few of the key actions
on screen. We had Blackstone's $83
billion BCRED fund see redemptions
equating to 7.9%
of its holdings with the company and
some of its senior employees actually
investing $400 million into the fund and
lifting the redemption restriction to
meet requests. Cliffwater's $33 billion
corporate lending fund saw withdrawal
requests surge to 14% leaving the
company to agree to purchase 7% of the
fund's shares. BlackRock and Morgan
Stanley adhered to their 5% restrictions
amid roughly 10% withdrawals. The $2
billion Lend X fund capped withdrawals
at 11% without disclosing the total
volume of requests. And the Blue Owl
Capital Corp II Business Development
Company, which has over $1.6 billion in
assets, temporarily restricted
redemptions in November and completely
halted redemptions in February as it
moved to sell assets and return capital
to its investors. With this just being
one of several Blue Owl funds impacted
by turmoil in the space. Now, while the
idea of trapping investors in their
holdings might sound exploitative or
nefarious, it is a fairly standard
mechanism for the private space. And the
truth is the whole point of the area is
to pursue investment opportunities not
otherwise available to the public
markets. It's argued that these illiquid
opportunities pay a higher return
premium, but that also means that
there's no secondary market to easily
offload these assets with investors
ready to buy by the second or minute.
So, the funds generally have to hold
their loans until maturity or enter
bilateral negotiations with other funds
or the business themselves to exit their
positions. So, to prevent investor
withdrawals impacting the fund's ability
to pursue these longer-term strategies,
it's pretty standard to have these
gating mechanisms. With it being
highlighted by the industry that the
gating mechanism is working as intended
to prevent a potentially more disruptive
fire sale in the space, especially as
gates from one fund can lead to a
contagion of investors trying to exit
other liquid positions. It's also why
the space has traditionally been
reserved for ultra high net worth
clients, family offices, and other
institutional investors like pensions
who can easily absorb that illiquidity
risk. However, a key factor that's
contributed to this rush for the exits
has been private credit's push into the
retail or individual investor space.
Last August, for example, Donald Trump
signed an executive order to allow
401(k)s to hold alternative assets like
private credit to democratize access,
and services like Robinhood have been
pushing to expand private investing
opportunities to retail investors. The
industry has also introduced things like
business development companies and
semi-liquid or evergreen funds that
allow for more regular withdrawals, such
as quarterly redemptions up to a certain
limit or percentage of the entire fund,
which has also increased access for
smaller investors. While all the funds
highlighted earlier, for example,
generally target affluent investors,
they're all geared towards the retail
segment and have easier access than
traditional private funds. So, there's
certainly the argument that part of this
friction is just that stylistic mismatch
that individual investors were sold
investment opportunities that weren't
necessarily appropriate. With J.P.
Morgan arguing that elevated redemption
requests are being driven more by
sentiment than fundamentals. And with
80% of the private credit investor base
still being institutional as of 2024
year end, the retail segment where
sentiment is the worst only represents a
fraction of the market. But even beyond
these sort of individual examples of
stress in the space, there have been
some more concerning fundamental issues
in private credit. One acute factor
that's been highlighted, for example,
has been AI's disruption to private
software companies, a space that private
credit just so happens to have outsized
exposure to. Business development
companies, for example, a private credit
vehicle that passes along the majority
of their income to investors, have,
according to Morgan Stanley, around a
quarter of their portfolios in software
companies. While private credit
collateralized loan obligations have
about a fifth of their portfolios in the
space. It also just so happens that
software loans have some of the highest
leverage and lowest coverage ratios
across major sectors, given the area's
history of strong cash flows and
profitability. And they're seeing a wall
of maturities fast approaching, with 31%
of debts coming due over the next two
years. We also, of course, now face a
very tricky macroeconomic environment
when compared to the past decade for
both these funds and the businesses that
are ultimately servicing these debts.
With tariffs, surging oil prices, a
sputtering labor market, and
importantly, much higher interest rates
adding pressure to the space. With the
last point being particularly notable
given that most private credit loans are
floating rate, meaning that those higher
rates are directly passed onto the
borrowing companies. And and frankly,
this is all building on top of
long-standing anxieties and concerns
with the private credit space. Given
the, again, private nature of these
investments, there's no secondary market
or price discovery with the investments
being held by these funds. Meaning that
their value often relies on appraisals,
which increases the risk of these rapid
write-offs when these companies are
incentivized to keep values high, to
keep fees high, and investors happy.
Even last year, we had concerns over the
rise of zombie funds, or private equity
funds that were holding onto their
assets longer than planned, continuing
to charge higher fees on higher
valuations, despite them seemingly
struggling to exit their positions.
There are also a few practices in the
space to ease liquidity issues that have
themselves raised a few eyebrows. As
some business development companies, for
example, allow for payments in kind,
meaning that the companies borrowing the
money here are able to make their
interest payments with either shares of
their own business or further debt.
Something that naturally increases the
risk of default when those debts come
due, especially given that this
mechanism is likely to be leaned on by
companies that are experiencing
difficulties with their cash flows. With
payments in kind representing around 13%
of BDC assets. We've also seen the
industry try to get around exit problems
with secondary market options like
continuation funds with the basic idea
there being a sponsor sets up a new fund
with new investors potentially more
better suited for the investment to
recycle the assets over to to allow the
older investors to get out of the
investment. A concept that's been
popular in the private equity space, but
we're starting to creep into the private
credit space, which is a bit bizarre
given that exits are supposed to be
baked into the original lending
arrangement. When you set terms for the
debt to be repaid in 7 years or so. Not
to mention that with the entire
secondary private credit market only
being around 100 billion dollars in
size, there's clearly limited capacity
for the two trillion dollar market. And
when you combine all this with the rapid
growth we've seen in the space, an
extended credit cycle, and a long period
of good times that potentially led to
excessive risk-taking from these private
credit funds, there are many who are
concerned that we're primed for a period
of higher default. With UBS estimating
that defaults in the space could reach
as high as 15%
in a worst-case scenario. Now, a key
difference here with the 2008 financial
crisis is that there does appear to be
less of that systemic risk. Investors
are most likely to be the ones to take a
direct hit here. Not to mention it's
fairly standard portfolio management
practice to limit alternative asset
allocations. And considering that the
space has traditionally catered to
institutions and ultra high net worth
individuals, you might think, "So what?
Who cares if a few family offices or
Warren Buffett types aren't able to
afford their X Force 145 super yacht
this year?" That being said, there would
still be wider implications from
pressures in the space. Outside the fact
that we do have individuals still
impacted because of that push into
retail, and of course pensions and even
insurance funds potentially having
exposure, which could hurt the
retirement savings and insurance payouts
for everyday people. Private credit is a
key lender to small and medium-sized
businesses. So, any turmoil in that
space could reduce credit availability,
which which could hurt the finances, the
business growth, and overall activity of
smaller businesses, which could also
translate into lower employment in those
areas. It could also have knock-on
effects for other credit markets,
especially given that private credit
funds themselves often borrow to
leverage their returns. Meaning that if
they lose money on their loans, it could
impact other lenders in the system,
which does actually, unfortunately, tie
all this back to the banks to an extent.
Because Moody's estimates that US banks
have lent $300 billion to private credit
funds, meaning that outside of their own
private credit operations, they
themselves could be impacted by
pressures in the space. Now, we have
seen some banks take steps to mitigate
this risk. Uh JPMorgan, for example,
recently marked down the value of some
loans being used as collateral by
private credit to ultimately reduce
their ability to borrow more money. But,
as you can imagine, limiting liquidity
at the same time that these funds are
experiencing higher investor redemption
requests could itself lead to some
issues rising to the surface. Now,
take a breath. I know that all sounds
pretty bad. Uh but before you start
crying in the town square that we're in
for another great financial crisis,
there are some considerations to keep in
mind. Firstly, again, private credit is
likely much less ingrained in the
financial system than what we saw back
in 2008. And even the bank exposure of
that $300 billion, for example, is
relatively small in the grand scheme of
loans lent by US banks. While Sparkle
specifically does have the highest
dollar exposure to these private credit
loans, but they still just represent 10%
of commercial loans, which actually
represents private credit's share of
total commercial loans, and 6% of the
bank's total loans. There's also not the
same derivative market like what we had
with mortgages during the financial
crisis to stack exposure on top of
exposure and amplify the impact of
higher defaults with these types of
debts. There could still be pain for
smaller banks who have higher than
average exposure, but all to say, we're
unlikely to have that same sort of
domino effect. These are also just some
red flags in the sea of data points out
there. BlackRock, for example, has
highlighted that non-accrual rates
remain below their 10-year average in
the private credit space, meaning that
many private credit loans are still
performing. High-yield credit spreads,
which measure the difference in yields
between riskier and safer bonds, also,
while slightly up, remain meaningfully
lower than they've been most of the past
decade, suggesting that markets still
have ample appetite for higher-risk
lending. Those payments in kind we
mentioned earlier haven't actually
increased as a percentage of overall
assets over the last few years. And
according to S&P Global, US speculative
grade default rates have actually
trended downwards in 2025, averaging
3.69% for the year. Also worth noting
that in the private credit space,
default rates can only be estimated,
which is why there's so much
variability. Fitch's figure, for
example, is based on a universe of just
302 companies. And the company actually
has another measure of private credit
defaults that incorporates analyst
adjustments that puts the default rate
at 5.4%. Fitch also suggests that the
higher default rates are concentrated
around smaller companies, with default
rates sitting at 15.8% for issuers with
EBITDA's of $25 million or less, versus
4% for issuers with EBITDA's of over
$100 million.
This also, of course, isn't indicative
that there isn't a problem, but the
space hasn't shown much evidence of
concern here. Many companies are still
aggressively pushing to expand their
private credit operations. Daniel
Leiter, an executive at Blackstone, has
argued that private credit is actually
safer than bank funding, given that
traditional lenders often have 10 times
the leverage of private credit funds.
And JP Morgan, Goldman Sachs, and Citi
have all reassured that their private
credit books are diversified and
high-grade, which, yes, you should take
with a heap of salt, uh but, you know,
still something worth highlighting.
However, it ultimately remains to be
seen how things will play out. Again, a
key issue here is how opaque the market
is and how little oversight we really
have over this type of activity. So, we
don't know how tangled the web of
relations is, how lax the lending
standards have become, or how much
leverage truly exists in the space when
you consider things like how much
leverage the investors may have taken on
with these investments. And it does
coincide with other pressures we've seen
in the financial markets. In Canada, for
example, where about $80 billion
Canadian is invested in private real
estate funds, about 40% of that amount
has been gated in the country amid a
real estate sell-off and liquidity
pressures. And with external factors
like the war in Iran and inflation, we
just have to wait and see how things
play out. That being said, hopefully
this video helped to put things into
perspective to highlight why this is an
important issue to keep an eye on, but
also why at this point it's far too
early to make claims of another
financial crisis. Thanks for watching. I
hope you found this video helpful. If
you did, please do make sure to like,
subscribe, all that good stuff. It does
help the channel tremendously. If you
want more content, you can check out
this video on why people hate private
equity. And let me know your thoughts on
today's topic in the comments below.
Thanks for watching and as always,
be safe out there.